[Glory]
[مجد]
[Episode 34]
[الحلقة 34]
Master Jianglai.
سيد جيانغلاي.
Huiqing refused to toast you.
رفضت هويتشينغ أن تهنئك.
Let me give you a toast.
اسمحوا لي أن أرفع لكم نخبًا.
Will you accept it?
هل ستقبل ذلك؟
You're the bold one.
أنت الشخص الجريء.
Do you know
هل تعلم
that Miss Rong by Jianglai's side
وجود الآنسة رونغ بجانب جيانغلاي
always has a whip with her?
هل تحمل معها سوطًا دائمًا؟
I've heard that every Rong Family woman is extremely jealous,
سمعت أن كل امرأة من عائلة رونغ شديدة الغيرة.
and men fear her as if she were a tiger.
ويخشاها الرجال كما لو كانت نمراً.
I'm afraid Jianglai
وأخشى جيانغلاي
won't dare to accept your toast.
لن يجرؤ أحد على قبول نخبك.
These are mere trifles,
هذه مجرد أمور تافهة،
not worth your anger, Master Jianglai.
لا يستحق الأمر غضبك يا سيد جيانغلاي.
Master Shuyu composed this music himself
قام الأستاذ شويو بتأليف هذه الموسيقى بنفسه
and had someone bring out
وأحضر أحدهم
this fine wine that has been preserved for 10 years.
هذا النبيذ الفاخر الذي تم حفظه لمدة 10 سنوات.
He has long awaited this reunion of brothers.
لقد انتظر طويلاً هذا اللقاء بين الإخوة.
Do not spoil his mood.
لا تفسد مزاجه.
Please drink this up.
تفضل بشرب هذا.
You'll be close brothers again.
ستعودان أخوين مقربين مرة أخرى.
Shuyu.
شويو.
I think you're truly drunk.
أعتقد أنك ثمل حقاً.
You should rest early tonight.
يجب أن تنام مبكراً الليلة.
Whatever it is,
مهما كان الأمر،
we can discuss it when you're sober.
يمكننا مناقشة الأمر عندما تكون في كامل وعيك.
He is so cold.
إنه بارد جداً.
I did nothing to offend him,
لم أفعل شيئاً يسيء إليه،
yet he treated me as if I were some filthy creature.
لكنه عاملني كما لو كنت مخلوقاً قذراً.
Master Shuyu, what about this wine?
يا سيد شويو، ما رأيك بهذا النبيذ؟
[Fuping Pavilion]
[جناح فوبينغ]
Uncle Jianglai.
العم جيانغلاي.
Uncle Jianglai!
العم جيانغلاي!
Xun, why are you here?
شون، لماذا أنت هنا؟
Uncle Jianglai,
العم جيانغلاي،
you ate nothing
لم تأكل شيئاً
at the table just now.
على الطاولة الآن.
This is for you.
هذا لك.
Xun, this jujube cake is from you.
شون، كعكة العناب هذه منك.
I will definitely eat it.
سآكله بالتأكيد.
It's cold outside. Go back early.
الجو بارد في الخارج. عد مبكراً.
Lady Shanbao, why are you not waiting in your chamber
سيدتي شانباو، لماذا لا تنتظرين في غرفتك؟
for Lord Lu to return?
هل سيعود اللورد لو؟
He specifically asked you to wait inside.
طلب منك تحديداً أن تنتظر في الداخل.
My mind is in a whirl.
عقلي مشوش.
I want to take a walk.
أريد أن أتمشى.
Xiu Qiong.
شيو تشيونغ.
Tonight,
الليلة،
did you notice if he seemed very happy
هل لاحظت ما إذا كان يبدو سعيدًا جدًا؟
when he left for the dinner?
متى غادر لتناول العشاء؟
Lord Lu lost his mother when he was young.
فقد اللورد لو والدته عندما كان صغيراً.
His foster father was killed by a powerful clan.
قُتل والده بالتبني على يد عشيرة قوية.
Left all alone in the world and with no one to rely on,
تُرك وحيداً في العالم بلا سند ولا أحد يعتمد عليه،
he endured nothing but bullying from his relatives
لم يتعرض إلا للتنمر من أقاربه
and cold stares from others.
ونظرات باردة من الآخرين.
Against all odds, he passed the imperial exam and became an official.
رغم كل الصعاب، اجتاز الامتحان الإمبراطوري وأصبح مسؤولاً.
He avenged his father, brought corrupt officials to justice,
لقد ثأر لأبيه، وقدم المسؤولين الفاسدين إلى العدالة،
and devoted himself to his duties.
وكرّس نفسه لواجباته.
Now he has finally reunited with his own elder brother.
والآن، التقى أخيراً بأخيه الأكبر.
Of course he's happy.
بالطبع هو سعيد.
Yes,
نعم،
he's happy.
إنه سعيد.
He's a reserved and reticent person.
إنه شخص متحفظ وكتوم.
I've never seen him
لم أره قط
show such obvious joy before.
أظهر فرحة واضحة من قبل.
Lady Shanbao, what troubles you?
سيدتي شانباو، ما الذي يزعجك؟
I hope I'm just overthinking.
أتمنى أن أكون أبالغ في التفكير.
May heaven be kind
أسأل الله أن يرحمها.
and let him
ودعه
keep this joy a little longer.
حافظ على هذه السعادة لفترة أطول قليلاً.
Lady Shanbao, your words sound odd.
سيدتي شانباو، كلماتك تبدو غريبة.
I don't quite follow.
لا أفهم تماماً.
Here come the jujube paste cakes.
وها هي كعكات معجون العناب.
The jujube paste cakes!
كعكات معجون العناب!
Be careful. It's hot!
انتبه، الجو حار!
It's so hot!
الجو حار جداً!
Mother.
الأم.
It burned my tongue.
لقد أحرق لساني.
Let me see.
دعني أرى.
No need to rush.
لا داعي للعجلة.
Let me cool it off for you.
دعني أهدئ الأمور من أجلك.
Take your time.
خذ وقتك.
Is it good?
هل هو جيد؟
It's really good!
إنه رائع حقاً!
Mother, your cooking is always the best.
يا أمي، طعامك هو الأفضل دائماً.
Mother.
الأم.
Shuyu also likes jujube cakes.
شويو يحب أيضاً كعكات العناب.
I learned that my mother back home
علمت أن والدتي في الوطن
has been suffering from her migraines again.
لقد عادت تعاني من الصداع النصفي مرة أخرى.
I thought of how this distant marriage
فكرت في كيف أن هذا الزواج البعيد
keeps me from my filial duties.
يمنعني ذلك من أداء واجباتي تجاه والديّ.
Miss Rong, I lost my composure
آنسة رونغ، لقد فقدت رباطة جأشي.
in front of you just now.
أمامك الآن.
Sorry you had to see that.
آسف لأنك اضطررت لرؤية ذلك.
Mrs. Xue.
السيدة شو.
When I was only 13,
عندما كنت في الثالثة عشرة من عمري فقط،
my grandmother forced me to escort tea shipments.
أجبرتني جدتي على مرافقة شحنات الشاي.
I had no choice but to leave
لم يكن لدي خيار سوى المغادرة
my nanny and maids
مربيتي وخادماتي
who had cared for me for years.
الذين اعتنوا بي لسنوات.
I cried my eyes out.
بكيتُ بكاءً شديداً.
The world collapsed around me.
انهار العالم من حولي.
Darkness swallowed me whole.
ابتلعتني الظلمة بالكامل.
My will to live was gone.
لقد فقدت رغبتي في الحياة.
I still remember that year
ما زلت أتذكر ذلك العام
we joined the autumn-winter caravan.
انضممنا إلى قافلة الخريف والشتاء.
It was over 3,000 kilometers,
كانت المسافة تزيد عن 3000 كيلومتر،
a journey that took 3 months.
رحلة استغرقت 3 أشهر.
Along the way were grasslands, mountains,
وعلى طول الطريق كانت هناك مراعي وجبال.
wild forests and desolate ruins.
غابات برية وأطلال مهجورة.
It felt like the journey would never end.
شعرت وكأن الرحلة لن تنتهي أبداً.
Thank you, Miss Rong.
شكراً لكِ يا آنسة رونغ.
Thanks for saving me from further embarrassment
شكراً لإنقاذي من المزيد من الإحراج
and even going out of your way to comfort me.
بل وحتى بذلت جهدًا إضافيًا لمواساتي.
Actually,
في الحقيقة،
Master Shuyu
المعلم شويو
wasn't always like this.
لم يكن الأمر دائماً هكذا.
[Bogu Studio]
[استوديو بوغو]
Let's go back now.
لنعد الآن.
Oh no!
يا إلهي!
My Lady, what should we do?
سيدتي، ماذا يجب أن نفعل؟
If we're caught
إذا تم القبض علينا
getting back late,
العودة متأخرة،
we'll never be
لن نكون أبداً
allowed to go out again.
يُسمح له بالخروج مرة أخرى.
My master happened to see you in a predicament.
لقد صادف أن رآك سيدي في مأزق.
He specifically sent me to bring you this umbrella
لقد أرسلني خصيصاً لأحضر لك هذه المظلة
to help you out.
لمساعدتك.
Who is your master?
من هو سيدك؟
A kind act needs no name attached to it.
لا يحتاج العمل الطيب إلى اسم.
Please just take it and use it.
تفضل بأخذه واستخدامه.
Thank you.
شكرًا لك.
He's a kind man who chooses to remain anonymous.
إنه رجل طيب يختار أن يبقى مجهول الهوية.
My Lady, let's hurry back.
سيدتي، فلنعد بسرعة.
Later, the Duke's family came to propose marriage.
وفي وقت لاحق، جاءت عائلة الدوق لطلب الزواج.
[Hengsheng]
[هنجشينج]
I've always despised
لطالما احتقرت
those spoiled and ignorant
أولئك المدللين والجاهلين
sons of nobility.
أبناء النبلاء.
So I deliberately stayed a year at my maternal grandparents' home,
لذلك تعمدت البقاء لمدة عام في منزل جدي وجدتي لأمي،
refusing to return home.
يرفض العودة إلى الوطن.
Later, my father tested Master Shuyu's scholarship
وفي وقت لاحق، اختبر والدي منحة الأستاذ شويو الدراسية
and tricked me into watching it from behind a screen.
وخدعني لأشاهده من خلف الشاشة.
I recognized him immediately.
تعرفت عليه على الفور.
It turned out his courtesy name was Hengsheng.
اتضح أن اسمه الأدبي هو هينغشنغ.
After I learned the whole story,
بعد أن عرفت القصة كاملة،
I thought he was truly my destined match
كنت أعتقد أنه كان حقًا شريك حياتي المقدر
and the man of my dreams.
ورجل أحلامي.
I was filled with such joy.
لقد غمرتني سعادة بالغة.
Hengsheng… Hengsheng…
هينجشينج... هينجشينج...
I thought it meant brimming with wit and wisdom.
ظننت أن معناها أنها تعني أنها مليئة بالذكاء والحكمة.
But actually, it meant
لكن في الواقع، كان ذلك يعني
that he was born in an unusual breech position,
أنه ولد في وضعية مقعدية غير معتادة،
which rendered the labor
مما جعل العمل
extremely perilous.
خطير للغاية.
That he bears such a name
أنه يحمل مثل هذا الاسم
is a testament to his rebellious
وهو دليل على تمرده
and defiant nature.
وطبيعتها المتمردة.
How could I rely on him for a lifetime?
كيف لي أن أعتمد عليه طوال حياتي؟
Someone's dead!
لقد مات أحدهم!
There's a dead man in the library!
هناك رجل ميت في المكتبة!
Jianglai is...
جيانغلاي ...
It's not him.
ليس هو.
Jianglai.
جيانغلاي.
Bao.
شنطة.
It's so cold.
الجو بارد جداً.
The maids screamed in terror
صرخت الخادمات من الرعب
when they saw the body.
عندما رأوا الجثة.
I hope you weren't frightened.
أتمنى ألا تكون قد شعرت بالخوف.
You never take
لا تأخذ أبدًا
this jade ring off.
هذا الخاتم المصنوع من اليشم يخلع.
The moment I saw it wasn't there, I knew it could not be you.
في اللحظة التي رأيت فيها أنه غير موجود، عرفت أنه لا يمكن أن يكون أنت.
Master Jianglai,
سيد جيانغلاي,
are you alright?
هل أنت بخير؟
Thank goodness you're in one piece.
الحمد لله أنك بخير.
Thank heavens!
الحمد لله!
This person
هذا الشخص
snuck into my room at night.
تسلل إلى غرفتي ليلاً.
Young Master!
يا سيدي الشاب!
With no way out,
بلا مخرج،
he swallowed his silver needle
ابتلع إبرته الفضية
and died on the spot.
ومات في الحال.
Mrs. Xue, what's wrong?
السيدة شو، ما الخطب؟
It's nothing.
لا شئ.
Miss Rong, unlike you, who have weathered many storms,
يا آنسة رونغ، على عكسك، فقد واجهتِ العديد من العواصف،
I am just a woman confined to the inner quarters.
أنا مجرد امرأة محصورة في الأماكن الداخلية.
The sight of a corpse
مشهد جثة
startled me for a moment.
أذهلني ذلك للحظة.
The smell of blood is indeed strong,
رائحة الدم قوية بالفعل،
making people dizzy.
مما يسبب الدوار للناس.
I have a vial of calming pills here.
لدي هنا قارورة من الحبوب المهدئة.
Mrs. Xue, please take one.
السيدة شو، تفضلي بأخذ واحدة.
It's excellent for settling your mind.
إنه ممتاز لتهدئة ذهنك.
Thank you.
شكرًا لك.
Son of a bitch!
ابن العاهرة!
This scoundrel somehow
هذا الوغد بطريقة ما
changed into a guard's uniform
ارتدى زي حارس أمن
and snuck into the mansion to carry out the assassination.
وتسلل إلى القصر لتنفيذ عملية الاغتيال.
Truly despicable!
حقير حقاً!
Thankfully, Master Jianglai was blessed by the gods
لحسن الحظ، حظي المعلم جيانغلاي ببركة الآلهة
and thus spared from harm.
وبذلك نجا من الأذى.
I'll go right away
سأذهب على الفور
to report this to the Duke!
إبلاغ الدوق بهذا الأمر!
We'll conduct a thorough search of the Duke's Mansion tonight
سنجري تفتيشًا دقيقًا لقصر الدوق الليلة
and find the assassin's accomplices!
واعثر على شركاء القاتل!
Do you really think his accomplices would just linger here
هل تعتقد حقاً أن شركاءه سيبقون هنا؟
waiting to be arrested by you?
هل تنتظر أن يتم القبض عليك؟
Yes.
نعم.
It's late.
إنه متأخر.
No need to make a fuss.
لا داعي لإثارة ضجة.
No need to disturb
لا داعي للإزعاج
the Duke and Master Shuyu.
الدوق والمعلم شويو.
Gather all the gatekeepers and patrol guards.
اجمعوا جميع حراس البوابات وحراس الدوريات.
Carry the body over there
انقل الجثة إلى هناك
and ask them to identify it.
واطلب منهم تحديدها.
Then send two men to keep watch over it.
ثم أرسل رجلين لمراقبته.
Tomorrow I'll send for a coroner to examine the corpse.
سأطلب غداً طبيباً شرعياً لفحص الجثة.
Master Jianglai,
سيد جيانغلاي,
you're truly thoughtful.
أنت شخصٌ مراعٍ حقاً.
But after tonight's fight,
لكن بعد نزال الليلة،
this chamber is hardly fit
هذه الغرفة بالكاد تصلح
for habitation anymore.
لم يعد صالحاً للسكن.
I'll immediately ask others
سأسأل الآخرين على الفور
to get another room prepared for you.
لتجهيز غرفة أخرى لك.
That won't be necessary.
لن يكون ذلك ضرورياً.
Tonight,
الليلة،
I'll make do with the study.
سأكتفي بالدراسة.
Huiqing, you were frightened
هويتشينغ، لقد كنتِ خائفة
and should go rest early.
وينبغي أن يذهب للراحة مبكراً.
Steward Xue,
المشرف شو،
please escort Huiqing back personally.
يرجى مرافقة هويتشينغ شخصياً للعودة.
Yes.
نعم.
Young Madam, please.
سيدتي الشابة، من فضلك.
I'll wait for you in the study.
سأنتظرك في غرفة الدراسة.
I have questions for you.
لدي أسئلة لك.
Take it away.
خذه بعيداً.
Bao.
شنطة.
I was just kicked
لقد تعرضت للركل للتو
by that assassin.
بواسطة ذلك القاتل.
It seems the blow struck deep inside.
يبدو أن الضربة أصابت في أعماق النفس.
I didn't feel a thing then,
لم أشعر بشيء حينها،
but now it suddenly hurts.
لكن الآن يؤلمني فجأة.
I can't bear it anymore, Bao.
لم أعد أحتمل ذلك يا باو.
I need to lie down for a while.
أحتاج إلى الاستلقاء لبعض الوقت.
Bao,
شنطة،
don't you care about me at all?
ألا تهتم لأمري على الإطلاق؟
I'm in such pain.
أشعر بألم شديد.
Come take a look.
تعالَ وألقِ نظرة.
Is it swollen from the kick?
هل هو متورم بسبب الركلة؟
Look. Is it right here?
انظر. هل هو هنا؟
Bao, how heartless you are!
باو، ما أقسى قلبك!
If you put on such an act to dodge my questions,
إذا تظاهرت بهذا الشكل للتهرب من أسئلتي،
then we're done talking.
إذن، انتهى حديثنا.
Bao.
شنطة.
Don't push me like this.
لا تدفعني هكذا.
Lu Jianglai, you dare not say it.
لو جيانغلاي، أنت لا تجرؤ على قول ذلك.
Fine, I'll say it for you.
حسناً، سأقولها نيابةً عنك.
Who hosted the feast you attended today?
من استضاف الوليمة التي حضرتها اليوم؟
What did you eat and drink there?
ماذا أكلت وشربت هناك؟
Someone wants you dead.
هناك من يريد موتك.
Are you truly unaware?
هل أنت جاهل حقاً؟
Or are you just playing dumb?
أم أنك تتظاهر بالغباء فقط؟
You elder brother, Master Shuyu...
أخي الأكبر، السيد شويو...
Say no more.
لا داعي للمزيد من الكلام.
You know everything perfectly well.
أنت تعرف كل شيء جيداً.
Why keep deceiving yourself?
لماذا تستمر في خداع نفسك؟
Before I met you,
قبل أن ألتقي بك،
I was cold-hearted and arrogant.
كنتُ قاسي القلب ومتغطرسًا.
Confronted by all the villains in the world,
في مواجهة جميع الأشرار في العالم،
I struck them down without mercy.
لقد سحقتهم بلا رحمة.
So many corrupt officials at court
يوجد العديد من المسؤولين الفاسدين في المحكمة
hated me and wanted me dead,
كانوا يكرهونني ويريدون موتي،
but I never flinched.
لكنني لم أتردد أبداً.
A person who is all alone
شخص وحيد تماماً
has nothing to fear.
ليس لديه ما يخشاه.
But just now,
لكن الآن فقط،
I was truly afraid.
كنت خائفاً حقاً.
For the first time in my life, I felt fear.
لأول مرة في حياتي، شعرت بالخوف.
What were you afraid of?
ممّ كنت تخاف؟
I was afraid that one day,
كنت أخشى أن يأتي يوم...
I would also become just a cold name
سأصبح أنا أيضاً مجرد اسم بارد
in those case files.
في ملفات تلك القضية.
I was even more afraid
كنت أكثر خوفاً.
that my elder brother
ذلك أخي الأكبر
was behind all this.
كان وراء كل هذا.
Bao, do you know what he did?
باو، هل تعلم ماذا فعل؟
He made little Xun
لقد صنع شون الصغير
bring me that jujube cake
أحضر لي كعكة العناب
laced with sedatives.
ممزوج بالمهدئات.
To reassure me,
لطمأنتي،
he even put on a show of humiliating his wife
بل إنه تظاهر بإذلال زوجته
and disciplining his son in front of me.
ويؤدب ابنه أمامي.
He is my only
هو كل ما أملك
blood brother
أخ بالدم
in this whole world.
في هذا العالم كله.
But he wants me dead.
لكنه يريد موتي.
Bao.
شنطة.
He wants me dead.
يريد موتي.
I see.
أرى.
You didn't eat that piece of jujube cake.
لم تأكل قطعة كعكة العناب تلك.
Well done.
أحسنت.
I kept that piece of jujube cake,
احتفظت بقطعة كعكة العناب تلك.
because I wanted to tell you
لأنني أردت أن أخبرك
that you were worrying too much,
أنك كنت قلقاً أكثر من اللازم،
that my brother
ذلك أخي
was as kind-hearted as my mother,
كانت طيبة القلب مثل أمي،
that he valued the bond between us siblings,
أنه كان يُقدّر الرابطة التي تجمعنا نحن الإخوة،
and that he was not as vile as you thought.
وأنه لم يكن بالسوء الذي كنت تظنه.
But in the end...
لكن في النهاية...
In the end,
في النهاية،
I, Lu Jianglai, am fated to be all alone
أنا، لو جيانغلاي، مقدر لي أن أكون وحيداً تماماً
and cut off from all kin.
وانقطعت صلته بجميع الأقارب.
No one in this world loves me.
لا أحد في هذا العالم يحبني.
No one in this world will ever love me.
لن يحبني أحد في هذا العالم أبداً.
But I'm here, aren't I?
لكنني هنا، أليس كذلك؟
You're not all alone.
لست وحدك.
Then, will you
إذن، هل ستفعل؟
by my side forever?
هل ستبقى بجانبي إلى الأبد؟
Rong Shanbao!
رونغ شانباو!
Do you have another lover?
هل لديك حبيب آخر؟
Why are you so hesitant and evasive
لماذا أنت متردد ومراوغ إلى هذا الحد؟
every time
في كل مرة
I ask you?
أنا أطلب منك؟
What are you hiding from me?
ما الذي تخفيه عني؟
Of course...
بالطبع...
This is exactly the tradition of your Rong family.
هذا هو بالضبط تقليد عائلة رونغ الخاصة بكم.
The moment I'm not by your side,
في اللحظة التي لا أكون فيها بجانبك،
someone will immediately
سيقوم شخص ما على الفور
take my place!
خذ مكاني!
Even if you're unwilling,
حتى لو كنت غير راغب،
your grandmother, your sisters,
جدتك، أخواتك،
and those
وهؤلاء
foolish men with ill intentions
رجال حمقى ذوو نوايا سيئة
will all try
سنحاول جميعاً
to deceive you with their sweet words.
ليخدعوك بكلماتهم المعسولة.
Who is it?
من هذا؟
Is it Cheng Guanyu?
هل هو تشنغ قوانيو؟
Or is it your cousin Wen Can?
أم أنه ابن عمك وين كان؟
Who the hell is it, Bao?
من هذا بحق الجحيم يا باو؟
Who the hell is it?
من هذا بحق الجحيم؟
Or which stranger is it?
أو أي غريب هذا؟
Tell me!
أخبرني!
Who the hell is it?
من هذا بحق الجحيم؟
I don't have another lover.
ليس لدي حبيب آخر.
Then promise me
ثم وعدني
that if you do,
وإذا فعلت ذلك،
you must tell me.
يجب أن تخبرني.
And what if I tell you?
وماذا لو أخبرتك؟
Then I will stuff
ثم سأقوم بالحشو
that despicable thief
ذلك اللص الحقير
back into his rat hole.
يعود إلى جحره.
And then I will hide you
ثم سأخفيك
in a place no one
في مكان لا أحد فيه
but me can ever find.
لكنني أستطيع أن أجدها.
Unless you swear
إلا إذا كنت تقسم
that you'll never leave me again
أنك لن تتركني مرة أخرى
and never abandon me again!
ولا تتخلى عني مرة أخرى!
♪ The music of fairies and jade flutes ♪
♪ موسيقى الجنيات ومزامير اليشم ♪
♪ The wine in the cup is as clear as jade dew with graceful sword dances ♪
♪ الخمر في الكأس صافٍ كقطرات الندى اليشمية مع رقصات السيوف الرشيقة ♪
Alright, alright.
حسناً، حسناً.
I promise you
أعدك
♪ There are refined scholars in white robes ♪
♪ هناك علماء مثقفون يرتدون أثوابًا بيضاء ♪
that there's absolutely no other lover.
أنه لا يوجد حبيب آخر على الإطلاق.
Although your anger is totally unwarranted,
على الرغم من أن غضبك غير مبرر على الإطلاق،
♪ The new hall is further adorned with intricate gold carvings ♪
♪ القاعة الجديدة مزينة بنقوش ذهبية متقنة ♪
I'm still glad
ما زلت سعيدًا
that I can pull you out of your sorrow
أنني أستطيع أن أخرجك من حزنك
♪ The sound of Konghou is echoing ♪
♪ يتردد صدى صوت الكونغ هو ♪
and despair.
واليأس.
You are Lu Jianglai, after all.
أنت لو جيانغلاي، بعد كل شيء.
♪ With a stroke of ink, I wrote a poem to show my passion ♪
♪ بضربة حبر، كتبت قصيدة لأُظهر شغفي ♪
Jiang Yiqian was so scheming,
كان جيانغ ييكيان يخطط لذلك،
cunning and ruthless,
ماكر وقاسٍ،
yet he couldn't intimidate you.
ومع ذلك، لم يستطع أن يرهبك.
♪ The jade-adorned robe and the long sword embody grace and talent ♪
♪ الرداء المزين باليشم والسيف الطويل يجسدان الرشاقة والموهبة ♪
As long as you don't care about him,
طالما أنك لا تهتم لأمره،
you are invincible.
أنت لا تُقهر.
♪ The mountains and rivers never miss the past ♪
♪ الجبال والأنهار لا تشتاق أبدًا للماضي ♪
I'll let you
سأتركك
dwell on your sorrow for just a little while.
تأمل في حزنك لفترة قصيرة.
♪ Writing poems to show my passion, I have no worry ♪
أكتب قصائد لأُظهر شغفي، لا أشعر بأي قلق.
Tomorrow morning,
صباح الغد،
you'll have to be yourself again.
سيتعين عليك أن تعود إلى طبيعتك مرة أخرى.
At least tonight,
على الأقل هذه الليلة،
at this very moment,
في هذه اللحظة بالذات،
♪ They say the Reclusive Immortal can hardly stay in the celestial palace ♪
♪ يقولون إن الخالد المنعزل بالكاد يستطيع البقاء في القصر السماوي ♪
I will go nowhere
لن أذهب إلى أي مكان
♪ Descending to the mortal world, he indulges in wine in a grand mansion ♪
♪ ينزل إلى عالم البشر، وينغمس في شرب الخمر في قصر فخم ♪
and stay right here by your side.
وسأبقى هنا بجانبك.
♪ Eyes full of affection ♪
♪ عيون مليئة بالمودة ♪
Really?
حقًا؟
♪ How many scrolls of poetry have been written with his ink? ♪
♪ كم عدد لفائف الشعر التي كُتبت بحبره؟ ♪
Of course.
بالطبع.
♪ Pouring the strongest wine in the world ♪
♪ نسكب أقوى أنواع النبيذ في العالم ♪
♪ Reclining on the lofty tower of Chang'an ♪
♪ مستلقيًا على برج تشانغآن الشاهق ♪
♪ Wondering who in the whole wide world could be carefree like him ♪
♪ أتساءل من في العالم كله يمكن أن يكون مرحاً مثله ♪
The guards in the mansion
الحراس في القصر
all claim they've never seen this person.
يدّعي الجميع أنهم لم يروا هذا الشخص قط.
I've ordered people to search the entire mansion.
لقد أمرت الناس بتفتيش القصر بأكمله.
I believe we'll get to the bottom of this soon.
أعتقد أننا سنصل إلى حقيقة هذا الأمر قريباً.
Your Highness, I hope
صاحب السمو، آمل
you can grant me three more days.
بإمكانك أن تمنحني ثلاثة أيام أخرى.
You just said
لقد قلت للتو
Jianglai had forbidden anyone in the mansion to look into this
منع جيانغلاي أي شخص في القصر من النظر في هذا الأمر.
and intended to bring in outside help, right?
وكان الهدف هو جلب مساعدة خارجية، أليس كذلك؟
Yes.
نعم.
So, he suspects there's an accomplice hidden in the mansion.
لذا، فهو يشتبه في وجود شريك مختبئ في القصر.
The fact that an assassin could sneak in so easily
حقيقة أن قاتلاً مأجوراً استطاع التسلل بهذه السهولة
proves you're all nothing but useless fools!
هذا يثبت أنكم جميعاً لستم سوى حمقى عديمي الفائدة!
Yes.
نعم.
The guards on patrol duty last night
الحراس الذين كانوا يقومون بدورياتهم الليلة الماضية
will each receive 30 lashes.
سيحصل كل منهم على 30 رمشًا.
Yes.
نعم.
Including you!
وأنت أيضاً!
Get out!
اخرج!
Yes.
نعم.
Xun.
سيء.
Come over to me.
تعال إليّ.
Grandfather.
الجد.
I've finished all the homework
لقد انتهيت من جميع الواجبات المنزلية
you assigned me.
لقد عيّنتني.
Really? Let me have a look.
حقاً؟ دعني ألقي نظرة.
Well done. Quite impressive.
أحسنت. عملٌ مثيرٌ للإعجاب حقاً.
Your Highness, I heard from Xun
صاحب السمو، لقد سمعت من شون
that you've been troubled lately.
أنك كنت تعاني من مشاكل مؤخراً.
I assume it's because
أفترض أن ذلك بسبب
you're concerned about Jianglai's matter.
أنت قلق بشأن قضية جيانغلاي.
I've made some Fuling cakes.
لقد صنعت بعض كعكات فولينغ.
The doctor says they can strengthen the vital energy,
يقول الطبيب إنها قادرة على تقوية الطاقة الحيوية،
calm the spirit,
تهدئة الروح،
and even promote longevity.
بل وتساهم في إطالة العمر.
This is the perfect season to have them.
هذا هو الموسم المثالي لامتلاكها.
You're thoughtful.
أنت شخص مراعٍ.
Leave them here.
اتركهم هنا.
Yes.
نعم.
Xun.
سيء.
Want some?
هل تريد بعضاً؟
Here you are.
تفضل.
Xun, you eat one first.
شون، تناول واحدة أولاً.
Thank you, Grandfather.
شكراً لك يا جدي.
No.
لا.
He hit you again?
هل ضربك مرة أخرى؟
I hurt myself
لقد آذيت نفسي
by accident.
عن طريق الصدفة.
It had nothing to do with him.
لم يكن له أي علاقة بالأمر.
-What a scoundrel! -Mother!
يا له من وغد! -أمي!
It's all right.
كل شيء على ما يرام.
Xun, don't be afraid.
شون، لا تخف.
I'm not talking about you.
أنا لا أتحدث عنك.
Grandfather, please eat it.
يا جدي، تفضل بتناوله.
You'll feel better after eating it.
ستشعر بتحسن بعد تناوله.
The Fuling cake tastes much better than the jujube cake.
طعم كعكة فولينغ أفضل بكثير من كعكة العناب.
The jujube cake?
كعكة العناب؟
Father told me to send it to Uncle Jianglai.
طلب مني والدي أن أرسلها إلى العم جيانغلاي.
What happened to your manners?
أين ذهبت أخلاقك؟
Before your grandfather, you must observe the strictest etiquette.
أمام جدك، يجب عليك مراعاة أشد قواعد السلوك صرامة.
Do not speak recklessly of matters
لا تتحدث بتهور عن الأمور
your elders have not asked about.
لم يسأل كبار السن لديك عن ذلك.
Your Highness, Xun has been suffering from indigestion.
صاحب السمو، يعاني شون من عسر الهضم.
He shouldn't eat too many pastries.
لا ينبغي له أن يأكل الكثير من المعجنات.
I'll take him back now.
سأعيده الآن.
Wait.
انتظر.
Xun, come over here.
شون، تعال إلى هنا.
You just said your father
لقد قلت للتو والدك
told you to send a jujube cake to your Uncle Jianglai.
قلت لك أن ترسل كعكة العناب إلى عمك جيانغلاي.
[Harmonious Radiance]
[إشراق متناغم]
Mr. Lang, this way, please.
السيد لانغ، من هنا من فضلك.
You're walking so slowly. It's driving me crazy!
أنت تمشي ببطء شديد. هذا الأمر يجننني!
Hurry up!
أسرع!
Shanbao chose to remain at the Duke's Mansion.
اختارت شانباو البقاء في قصر الدوق.
She must have her reasons.
لا بد أن لديها أسبابها.
You
أنت
rushed over in such a panic
هرعوا إلى هناك في حالة من الذعر الشديد
only because of the mission Grandmother gave you.
فقط بسبب المهمة التي أوكلتها إليك جدتك.
Grandmother carefully selected
اختارت الجدة بعناية
these men for Shanbao.
هؤلاء الرجال لشانباو.
You already have Mr. Bai by your side.
لديك بالفعل السيد باي بجانبك.
Don't even think about it.
لا تفكر في الأمر حتى.
Grandmother said she was done meddling,
قالت الجدة إنها اكتفت من التدخل.
yet only a few days later,
ولكن بعد بضعة أيام فقط،
she's already worrying again.
إنها تشعر بالقلق مجدداً.
As long as Shanbao doesn't neglect her duties,
طالما أن شانباو لا تهمل واجباتها،
what does it matter who she likes?
ما أهمية من تحب؟
I wouldn't put it that way.
لن أطرح الأمر بهذه الطريقة.
Lu Jianglai is about to be formally recognized
لو جيانغلاي على وشك أن يتم الاعتراف به رسمياً
as the Duke's son.
بصفته ابن الدوق.
Soon, he'll be matched with some noble lady from a prominent family.
قريباً، سيتم تزويجه بسيدة نبيلة من عائلة مرموقة.
Shanbao can't fall behind.
لا يمكن لشانباو أن يتخلف عن الركب.
This time,
هذه المرة،
Grandmother personally selected more than 10 candidates,
اختارت الجدة شخصياً أكثر من 10 مرشحين،
each rivaling him in both appearance and talent.
كل منهم ينافسه في المظهر والموهبة.
Not just the families from Jiangnan are eager to make a move.
ليست العائلات من جيانغنان وحدها هي المتشوقة للانتقال.
Even Cousin Wen
حتى ابن العم وين
has sent two letters to ask about it.
وقد أرسل رسالتين للاستفسار عن ذلك.
This is the Duke of Yongguo's Mansion.
هذا هو قصر دوق يونغقو.
Lu Jianglai isn't someone to mess with.
لو جيانغلاي ليس شخصاً يُستهان به.
I advise you
أنصحك
to put away this precious booklet at once.
أن أضع هذا الكتيب الثمين جانباً على الفور.
Otherwise, if he finds out...
وإلا، إذا اكتشف ذلك...
How about
ماذا عن
I take a look for Shanbao and see which one stands out?
أبحث عن مطعم شانباو وأرى أيها يبرز؟
Hurry! Hide it away!
أسرع! أخفه!
Excuse me,
اعذرني،
could you please return my ball?
هل يمكنك من فضلك إعادة الكرة لي؟
This little girl has such beautiful features.
تتمتع هذه الطفلة الصغيرة بملامح جميلة للغاية.
So pretty.
جميلة جداً.
What's your name?
ما اسمك؟
Why are you playing here alone?
لماذا تلعب هنا بمفردك؟
My name is Xuanyu.
اسمي شوانيو.
I'm not alone.
لست وحدي.
I'm with...
أنا مع...
Lady Xuanyu!
سيدة شوانيو!
Lady Xuanyu,
السيدة شيوانيو،
I just went back to fetch something,
لقد عدت للتو لأحضر شيئاً ما.
and in the blink of an eye, you ran off.
وفي لمح البصر، هربت.
Madam Chang will be worried if she can't find you.
ستشعر السيدة تشانغ بالقلق إذا لم تتمكن من العثور عليك.
Let's go.
دعنا نذهب.
If only I had
لو أنني فقط...
such a clever and adorable daughter.
يا لها من ابنة ذكية ورائعة.
I should keep
ينبغي عليّ أن أحتفظ
one man from the booklet for myself.
رجل واحد من الكتيب لنفسي.
What are you looking at?
ما الذي تنظر إليه؟
Nothing. Let's go.
لا شيء. هيا بنا.
When did those outsiders arrive at the mansion?
متى وصل هؤلاء الغرباء إلى القصر؟
Find out and report back.
اكتشف الأمر وأبلغنا بالنتائج.
Yes.
نعم.
The coroner retrieved
استعاد الطبيب الشرعي
the silver needle that the deceased
الإبرة الفضية التي كان المتوفى
had swallowed.
ابتلع.
Since the pathways within the head
بما أن المسارات داخل الرأس
are all linked, even a needle this fine,
كلها مترابطة، حتى إبرة بهذه الدقة.
when driven with precisely calculated force,
عند تشغيلها بقوة محسوبة بدقة،
could pierce through the ear canal into the brain,
قد تخترق قناة الأذن لتصل إلى الدماغ،
causing instant death.
مما يؤدي إلى الموت الفوري.
Afterwards, the needle could
بعد ذلك، يمكن أن تكون الإبرة
be pulled out without a trace.
يتم سحبها دون أن تترك أثراً.
Even after the coroner's examination,
حتى بعد فحص الطبيب الشرعي،
no evidence would be found.
لن يتم العثور على أي دليل.
Judging
الحكم
from how the assassin committed suicide,
من خلال كيفية انتحار القاتل،
he was clearly very professional.
كان من الواضح أنه محترف للغاية.
A highly paid assassin?
قاتل مأجور بأجر مرتفع؟
Who have you offended, My Lord?
من أسأت إليه يا سيدي؟
They even dared to break into the Duke's Mansion to kill you.
بل إنهم تجرأوا على اقتحام قصر الدوق لقتلك.
I'll be more careful.
سأكون أكثر حذراً.
Thank you for your help.
شكرا لك على مساعدتك.
My Lord, since you've asked me to be your helper,
يا سيدي، بما أنك طلبت مني أن أكون معينك،
why won't you speak plainly?
لماذا لا تتحدث بوضوح؟
Is there
هل يوجد
anything you can't bring yourself to say?
هل هناك أي شيء لا تستطيع أن تجبر نفسك على قوله؟
I...
أنا...
My Lord, Mrs. Xue is here.
سيدي، السيدة شو هنا.
Let her in.
أدخلها.
Jianglai, I've come unbidden to beg for your help.
جيانغلاي، لقد جئت دون دعوة لأتوسل إليك طلباً للمساعدة.
Please, don't say that.
من فضلك، لا تقل ذلك.
You can just tell me what's happened.
يمكنك فقط أن تخبرني بما حدث.
Your brother
أخوك
has been taken away by the Duke's men.
تم أخذها من قبل رجال الدوق.
I beg you to put aside past grievances
أرجوكم أن تتجاوزوا ضغائن الماضي
and save his life.
وإنقاذ حياته.
Save his life?
إنقاذ حياته؟
The Duke truly has sharp eyes
يتمتع الدوق بنظر حاد حقًا
and sees through every ruse.
ويكشف كل حيلة.
He knows
هو يعلم
everything
كل شئ
you've done.
لقد فعلت ذلك.
I advise you to admit your fault
أنصحك بالاعتراف بخطئك
and beg for forgiveness.
ويتوسل طلباً للمغفرة.
Father, I am foolish
يا أبي، أنا أحمق
and don't know what I've done wrong.
ولا أعرف ما الخطأ الذي ارتكبته.
Father, I beg you to tell me my fault.
يا أبي، أتوسل إليك أن تخبرني بخطئي.
You asked Xun to send the jujube cake, didn't you?
لقد طلبت من شون أن يرسل كعكة العناب، أليس كذلك؟
Yes, I asked him to send it.
نعم، طلبت منه أن يرسلها.
Someone laced the jujube cake with sleeping draughts,
قام أحدهم بوضع جرعات منومة في كعكة العناب .
which were enough to make a person unconscious.
والتي كانت كافية لجعل الشخص فاقداً للوعي.
Do you know that your brother
هل تعلم أن أخاك
was attacked by assassins last night?
هل تعرض لهجوم من قبل قتلة مأجورين الليلة الماضية؟
I...
أنا...
I knew nothing about it.
لم أكن أعرف شيئاً عن ذلك.
Fine.
بخير.
Then the beating will continue,
ثم سيستمر الضرب،
until you admit what you know!
إلى أن تعترف بما تعرفه!
Father, you suspect
يا أبي، أنت تشك
I'm the one who wants to kill Jianglai?
أنا من يريد قتل جيانغلاي؟
Other than you,
باستثنائك،
who else hates him so deeply?
من غيره يكرهه بشدة؟
From the very day I brought
منذ اليوم الذي أحضرت فيه
Jianglai into this mansion,
جيانغلاي إلى هذا القصر،
you've been guarding against him, sowing discord between us,
لقد كنت تحمينا منه، وتزرع الفتنة بيننا.
and trying every means to drive him out!
ومحاولة بكل الوسائل طرده!
His servant
خادمه
managed to get out of the mansion and send word outside.
تمكن من الخروج من القصر وإرسال رسالة إلى الخارج.
Wasn't it you who pulled the strings?
ألم تكن أنت من يحرك الخيوط؟
I simply didn't bother
لم أكلف نفسي عناء ذلك ببساطة
to expose such petty tricks.
لكشف هذه الحيل التافهة.
I am a cripple,
أنا معاق،
who cannot uphold the Xue family's name.
الذين لا يستطيعون الحفاظ على اسم عائلة شو.
Everyone in the mansion knows
الجميع في القصر يعلمون
that you brought him back
أنك أعدته
to replace me!
ليحل محلي!
So it's only natural that I was wary of him
لذلك فمن الطبيعي أن أكون حذراً منه
and kept my distance!
وحافظت على مسافة بيننا!
Is that such a grave crime?
هل هذه جريمة خطيرة؟
But I never sent anyone to kill him.
لكنني لم أرسل أحداً لقتله.
Never!
أبداً!
I can swear to God!
أقسم بالله!
You still dare to deny it?
هل ما زلت تجرؤ على إنكار ذلك؟
You're mediocre yourself,
أنت نفسك شخص متوسط ​​المستوى،
yet you're jealous of those with talent.
لكنك تغار من أصحاب المواهب.
You even want to harm
بل إنك تريد أن تؤذي
your own brother.
أخوك.
You're truly monstrous!
أنت وحش حقيقي!
I'll give you one last chance.
سأمنحك فرصة أخيرة.
If you did it, admit it.
إذا فعلت ذلك، فاعترف به.
Be a man and take responsibility for your deeds!
كن رجلاً وتحمل مسؤولية أفعالك!
It wasn't me!
لم أكن أنا!
I plead not guilty!
أُقرّ ببراءتي!
I never thought
لم أكن أتخيل ذلك أبداً
that jealousy could breed
قد تؤدي الغيرة إلى
such a beastly heart
قلب وحشي
in my own son,
في ابني،
driving him to commit this inhumane crime.
مما دفعه لارتكاب هذه الجريمة اللاإنسانية.
Take him away!
خذوه بعيداً!
Cleanse his wicked heart with water!
طهّر قلبه الشرير بالماء!
Master Shuyu, forgive me.
يا أستاذ شويو، سامحني.
Father!
أب!
I didn't do it!
لم أفعل ذلك!
I never sent anyone to assassinate my brother!
لم أرسل أحداً لاغتيال أخي!
Someone was deliberately framing me!
كان أحدهم يدبر لي مكيدة عن عمد!
Father, don't be deceived by them!
يا أبي، لا تنخدع بهم!
Father!
أب!
Look at this Mr. Ye.
انظر إلى هذا يا سيد يي.
He is handsome and well-educated.
إنه وسيم ومتعلم جيداً.
His looks can rival those of the paragons of male beauty.
يمكن أن يضاهي مظهره مظهر نماذج الجمال الذكوري.
It is said that every time he goes out,
يقال إنه في كل مرة يخرج فيها،
he attracts crowds of women,
إنه يجذب حشوداً من النساء،
his carriage filled with gifts from admirers.
عربته مليئة بالهدايا من المعجبين.
He also comes from an esteemed family,
وهو أيضاً ينتمي إلى عائلة مرموقة.
proud and arrogant.
فخور ومتغطرس.
He's determined
إنه مصمم
to marry a noble lady of both beauty and talent.
أن يتزوج سيدة نبيلة تتمتع بالجمال والموهبة.
Girls from ordinary families could never hope to match him.
لا يمكن للفتيات من العائلات العادية أن يأملن أبداً في منافسته.
I'm discussing important matters with Yunshu.
أنا أناقش أموراً مهمة مع يونشو.
Do not disrupt us.
لا تعرقلوا عملنا.
I'm here
أنا هنا
on Grandmother's orders.
بناءً على أوامر جدتي.
How is that disrupting anything?
كيف يُسبب ذلك أي اضطراب؟
Take another look.
ألقِ نظرة أخرى.
If you don't like this one, you can choose another.
إذا لم يعجبك هذا الخيار، يمكنك اختيار خيار آخر.
Xiu Qiong, you should have spoken up earlier.
شيو تشيونغ، كان عليكِ أن تتحدثي في ​​وقت سابق.
I thought
ظننت
it was that jealous man coming over.
كان ذلك الرجل الغيور هو من جاء.
Lady Shanbao.
سيدة شانباو.
The Duke is interrogating Master Shuyu.
الدوق يستجوب السيد Shuyu.
Lord Lu has rushed over to Baoshi Hall.
هرع اللورد لو إلى قاعة باوشي.
Lord Lu is facing a difficult matter,
يواجه اللورد لو مسألة صعبة،
and you won't help him?
ولن تساعده؟
Whether it's difficult, domestic, joyous
سواء كان الأمر صعباً، أو منزلياً، أو مبهجاً
or disastrous
أو كارثي
all depends on his decision.
كل شيء يتوقف على قراره.
Others can't help him.
لا يستطيع الآخرون مساعدته.
In the end, he must make the decision himself.
في النهاية، عليه أن يتخذ القرار بنفسه.
Yunshu, I have to trouble you
يونشو، عليّ أن أزعجك
to look into someone for me.
أن يبحث في أمر شخص ما نيابة عني.
I really didn't do it.
لم أفعل ذلك حقاً.
It's freezing cold!
الجو بارد جداً!
You've finally come to see me.
لقد أتيت لرؤيتي أخيراً.
This damn wretch
هذا الوغد اللعين
dared to plot to kill his own brother.
تجرأ على التخطيط لقتل شقيقه.
I am seeking justice for you.
أسعى لتحقيق العدالة لك.
You need not stop them.
لستَ مضطراً لإيقافهم.
Even if he were
حتى لو كان
truly guilty of murder,
مذنب حقاً بجريمة القتل،
you couldn't just take the law into your own hands.
لا يمكنك ببساطة أن تأخذ القانون بيدك.
As for me,
أما أنا،
I don't need you to seek justice for me.
لست بحاجة إليك لتسعى لتحقيق العدالة لي.
You're unworthy.
أنت لا تستحق.
How dare you!
كيف تجرؤ!
Your Highness, be careful!
يا صاحب السمو، كن حذراً!
I truly did not misjudge you.
لم أخطئ في تقديرك حقاً.
Our Xue family finally has a worthy heir.
أخيرًا، أصبح لعائلة شو وريث جدير.
Bring Xun out!
أخرجوا شون!
Yes.
نعم.
Look.
ينظر.
Even your own son
حتى ابنك
isn't willing to plead for you.
ليس مستعداً للتوسل من أجلك.
What a pathetic failure
يا له من فشل بائس!
you are as a father!
أنت كأب!
Jianglai, this is your own nephew.
جيانغلاي، هذا ابن أخيك.
When you inherit my title,
عندما ترث لقبي،
you must treat him and his mother well.
يجب عليك أن تعامله هو وأمه معاملة حسنة.
As for your
أما بالنسبة لك
good-for-nothing brother,
أخي عديم الفائدة،
he shall be exiled to a monastery to live in seclusion
سيُنفى إلى دير ليعيش في عزلة.
and atone for his sins for the rest of his life.
ويكفّر عن ذنوبه طوال حياته.
How do you know I am capable of shouldering the responsibility?
كيف تعرف أنني قادر على تحمل المسؤولية؟
I have kept a close eye on you for quite some time.
لقد راقبتك عن كثب لفترة طويلة.
What you've done in Linjin
ما فعلته في لينجين
shows that you're resolute
يدل ذلك على أنك حازم
and decisive.
وحاسمة.
You are the spitting image
أنت نسخة طبق الأصل
of my younger self!
أنا في صغري!
How could I possibly be mistaken?
كيف يمكن أن أكون مخطئاً؟
Fine.
بخير.
You asked me to treat Xun well.
لقد طلبت مني أن أعامل شون معاملة حسنة.
But when Xun grows up
لكن عندما يكبر شون
and asks me
ويسألني
why I seized his father's title
لماذا استوليت على لقب والده
and drove his father out of the Xue family,
وطرد والده من عائلة شويه،
how should I answer him?
كيف أجيبه؟
Shuyu is willing to step aside.
شويو مستعد للتنحي جانباً.
You didn't seize anything.
لم تستولوا على أي شيء.
Everything in this household
كل شيء في هذا المنزل
will be given to you by me.
سأقدمها لك.
Who dares to question that?
من يجرؤ على التشكيك في ذلك؟
Jianglai, what I want is a wolf.
جيانغلاي، ما أريده هو ذئب.
I want a leader wolf that can command the pack.
أريد ذئباً قائداً يستطيع قيادة القطيع.
Everything I earned on the battlefield
كل ما كسبته في ساحة المعركة
can only be given to someone
لا يمكن إعطاؤها إلا لشخص ما
who will bring glory to our Xue family.
من سيجلب المجد لعائلة شويه.
Xun is too young,
شون صغير جداً،
but you are in your prime!
لكنك في أوج عطائك!
So your plan is that I replace my elder brother,
إذن خطتك هي أن أحل محل أخي الأكبر،
and my nephew succeeds me.
ويخلفني ابن أخي.
But what if I have children of my own in the future
لكن ماذا لو أنجبت أطفالاً في المستقبل؟
and refuse to give the title to Xun?
ورفض منح اللقب لـ Xun؟
Power and titles
السلطة والألقاب
only breed more hatred
لن يؤدي ذلك إلا إلى زيادة الكراهية
and agony,
والمعاناة،
just like they did to you.
تمامًا كما فعلوا بك.
You already had
كان لديك بالفعل
a beloved wife,
زوجة محبوبة،
yet to get more heirs,
ولم يرزق بعد بالمزيد من الورثة،
you took one concubine after another.
اتخذت محظية تلو الأخرى.
You brought them into this household,
لقد أدخلتهم إلى هذا المنزل،
but you did nothing to stop your wife's jealousy,
لكنك لم تفعل شيئاً لوقف غيرة زوجتك،
standing by as they were bullied!
وقفوا مكتوفي الأيدي بينما كانوا يتعرضون للتنمر!
You drove my mother into a life of wandering,
لقد دفعتِ أمي إلى حياة الترحال،
leaving her with no one to rely on.
مما تركها بلا أحد تعتمد عليه.
You made me suffer all the hardships of the world
لقد جعلتني أعاني من كل مصاعب العالم
and endure the cold stares of others!
وتحمّل نظرات الآخرين الباردة!
They all said I was a servant's son.
قالوا جميعاً إنني ابن خادم.
But so what?
ولكن ما الفائدة من ذلك؟
The lowborn servant
الخادم الوضيع
was willing to take my mother and me in.
كان على استعداد لاستقبالي أنا وأمي.
He spent everything he had
أنفق كل ما يملك
supporting my education.
دعم تعليمي.
His moral character
شخصيته الأخلاقية
was a thousand times nobler than yours.
كان أنبل بألف مرة من نبلك.
What did you say?
ماذا قلت؟
I said you're selfish!
قلت لك إنك أناني!
You imprisoned me in your mansion,
لقد سجنتني في قصرك،
not because you missed
ليس لأنك أخطأت
your long-lost son.
ابنك الذي فقدته منذ زمن طويل.
You never cared how much I had suffered
لم تهتم أبدًا بمدى معاناتي
or what hardships I had endured.
أو ما هي المصاعب التي تحملتها.
You really think
هل تعتقد حقاً
that I would be grateful and overjoyed
سأكون ممتناً وسعيداً للغاية.
when offered
عند العرض
this title?
هذا العنوان؟
You didn't even bother to ask
لم تكلف نفسك عناء السؤال
when my mother passed away,
عندما توفيت والدتي،
or where she was buried!
أو أين دُفنت!
You don't deserve to be her husband!
أنت لا تستحق أن تكون زوجها!
Your actions
أفعالك
have made my own brother fear me.
لقد جعلت أخي يخشاني.
He fears that I will usurp his noble title.
يخشى أن أغتصب لقبه النبيل.
He even fears that I'll drive him to his death.
بل إنه يخشى أن أتسبب في موته.
He's my brother.
إنه أخي.
He and I share the same mother!
أنا وهو نشترك في نفس الأم!
Yet you are
لكنك
forcing us to turn against each other
مما يجبرنا على الانقلاب على بعضنا البعض
with your own hands!
بيديك!
You
أنت
don't deserve to be our father!
لا يستحق أن يكون والدنا!
I was fighting battles on the front lines.
كنت أخوض معارك على الخطوط الأمامية.
How could I have cared
كيف كان بإمكاني أن أهتم؟
about my women's petty jealousies?
ماذا عن غيرة النساء التافهة؟
It pains me deeply that you and your mother
يؤلمني بشدة أنك أنت ووالدتك
were driven out of the mansion.
طُردوا من القصر.
As for your brother,
أما بالنسبة لأخيك،
his jealousy toward you
غيرته تجاهك
stems from his own narrow-mindedness.
ينبع ذلك من ضيق أفقه.
Do you understand?
هل تفهم؟
Shuyu.
شويو.
Let's go.
دعنا نذهب.
Hate me if you must.
اكرهني إن شئت.
But if you give up everything
لكن إذا تخليت عن كل شيء
in the Duke's Mansion just out of hatred,
في قصر الدوق بدافع الكراهية فقط،
then you'll truly be
حينها ستكون حقاً
the biggest fool in the world!
أكبر أحمق في العالم!
Your Highness, this...
صاحب السمو، هذا...
A man who has lost all hope
رجل فقد كل أمل
wouldn't argue so fiercely.
لن أجادل بهذه الشراسة.
He cares about his brother
إنه يهتم بأخيه
and even more about his nephew.
بل وأكثر من ذلك عن ابن أخيه.
In the end,
في النهاية،
he will lower
سيخفض
his proud head in front of me.
رأسه الفخور أمامي.
Here.
هنا.
Hurry! Bring the brazier!
أسرعوا! أحضروا الموقد!
The brazier! Hurry!
الموقد! أسرعوا!
Are you feeling better?
هل تشعر بتحسن؟
Master Shuyu,
الأستاذ شويو،
I heard you had caught a cold,
سمعت أنك أصبت بنزلة برد،
so I specially prepared some ginger soup for you.
لذلك قمتُ بتحضير حساء الزنجبيل خصيصاً لك.
Drink it while it's hot. It'll ward off the cold.
اشربه ساخناً. سيقيك من البرد.
You...
أنت...
Get out.
اخرج.
Master Shuyu,
الأستاذ شويو،
why is your face deathly pale?
لماذا وجهك شاحب كالموت؟
It's so frightening.
إنه أمر مرعب للغاية.
Why not let me
لماذا لا تدعني؟
stay here and attend to you?
هل ستبقى هنا لأعتني بك؟
Get out!
اخرج!
Yes, Master Shuyu.
نعم، يا سيد شويو.
Do drink the soup while it's still hot.
اشرب الحساء وهو لا يزال ساخناً.
It won't be effective if it turns cold.
لن يكون فعالاً إذا أصبح الجو بارداً.
And all my effort will be wasted.
وسيذهب كل جهدي سدى.
Let me do it.
دعني أفعل ذلك.
When I was little,
عندما كنت صغيراً،
Mother used to comb my hair.
كانت أمي تمشط شعري.
It's a pity that I didn't understand back then
من المؤسف أنني لم أفهم ذلك حينها.
why she always made two portions
لماذا كانت دائماً تعد حصتين
of jujube cakes every time.
من كعكات العناب في كل مرة.
She would often stare at me blankly.
كانت تحدق بي غالباً بنظرة فارغة.
I only realized later
لم أدرك ذلك إلا لاحقا
that Mother
تلك الأم
was missing her other son.
كانت تفتقد ابنها الآخر.
Before Mother passed away,
قبل وفاة والدتي،
she held my hand tightly, refusing to close her eyes.
أمسكت بيدي بقوة، ورفضت أن تغمض عينيها.
She was unwilling to go.
لم تكن راغبة في الذهاب.
She couldn't accept that before she died,
لم تستطع تقبّل ذلك قبل وفاتها.
she never got to see you one last time.
لم تتح لها الفرصة لرؤيتك للمرة الأخيرة.
All right.
حسنًا.
So, Shuyu, you don't need to worry.
لذا يا شويو، لا داعي للقلق.
I will never fight you for anything.
لن أقاتلك أبداً على أي شيء.
You don't want to fight me,
أنت لا تريد أن تقاتلني،
but I did think about killing you.
لكنني فكرت في قتلك.
I couldn't bring myself to do it.
لم أستطع أن أجبر نفسي على فعل ذلك.
I hesitated.
ترددت.
Jianglai, believe me.
جيانغلاي، صدقني.
I never sent anyone to kill you.
لم أرسل أحداً لقتلك.
If I really had done it,
لو كنت قد فعلت ذلك حقاً،
may I be pierced by a thousand arrows
أتمنى أن تخترقني ألف سهم
and die a horrible death.
ويموت ميتة بشعة.
All right. I see.
حسناً، فهمت.
Don't be distressed.
لا تقلق.
It's getting late.
لقد تأخر الوقت.
Shuyu, get some rest.
شويو، خذ قسطاً من الراحة.
I'll come to see you another day.
سأزورك في يوم آخر.
Jianglai!
جيانغلاي!
I know you don't believe me.
أعلم أنك لا تصدقني.
But
لكن
could you tell me more about her?
هل يمكنك إخباري المزيد عنها؟
[Two ways to pronounce the words for tea in different languages]
[طريقتان لنطق كلمة "شاي" في لغات مختلفة]
Bao.
شنطة.
I was just kicked
لقد تعرضت للركل للتو
by that assassin.
بواسطة ذلك القاتل.
It seems the blow struck deep inside.
يبدو أن الضربة أصابت في أعماق النفس.
I didn't feel a thing then,
لم أشعر بشيء حينها،
but now it suddenly hurts.
لكن الآن يؤلمني فجأة.
I can't bear it anymore, Bao.
لم أعد أحتمل ذلك يا باو.
I need to lie down for a while.
أحتاج إلى الاستلقاء لبعض الوقت.
Bao,
شنطة،
don't you care about me at all?
ألا تهتم لأمري على الإطلاق؟
I'm in such pain.
أشعر بألم شديد.
Come take a look.
تعالَ وألقِ نظرة.
Is it swollen from the kick?
هل هو متورم بسبب الركلة؟
[The language of tea knows no borders]
[لغة الشاي لا تعرف حدوداً]
With the global expansion of the tea trade,
مع التوسع العالمي لتجارة الشاي،
the development of tea culture
تطور ثقافة الشاي
has also swept the world.
وقد اجتاحت العالم أيضاً.
As many people know,
كما يعلم الكثيرون،
in different languages around the world,
بلغات مختلفة حول العالم،
with a few exceptions,
باستثناءات قليلة،
there are only two ways
لا يوجد سوى طريقين
to pronounce the words for tea:
كيفية نطق كلمات كلمة "شاي":
"cha" or "tea."
"cha" أو "شاي".
For instance, it's "cha"
على سبيل المثال، إنها "تشا"
in Russian and Korean,
باللغتين الروسية والكورية،
while it's "tea"
بينما هو "شاي"
in French and Spanish.
باللغتين الفرنسية والإسبانية.
Why does tea from China
لماذا الشاي الصيني
have two different pronunciations?
هل لها نطقان مختلفان؟
This is mainly
هذا بشكل رئيسي
because Chinese tea
بسبب الشاي الصيني
was introduced to overseas regions
تم تقديمه إلى المناطق الخارجية
in different ways.
بطرق مختلفة.
The regions
المناطق
that imported tea from nothern China via the Land Silk Road
ذلك الشاي المستورد من شمال الصين عبر طريق الحرير البري
or through tributary trade
أو من خلال التجارة التابعة
were more likely
كانوا أكثر عرضة
to have interactions with northern China.
لإقامة علاقات مع شمال الصين.
Most areas in northern China
معظم المناطق في شمال الصين
refer to tea as "cha."
يشير إلى الشاي باسم "تشا".
As a result,
نتيجة ل،
the regions that obtained tea
المناطق التي حصلت على الشاي
via the Land Silk Road
عبر طريق الحرير البري
and tributary trade
والتجارة التابعة
almost all adopted the pronunciation of "cha"
اعتمد الجميع تقريباً نطق "cha"
or a similar variant of it.
أو صيغة مشابهة لها.
As the Maritime Silk Road
باعتباره طريق الحرير البحري
rose to prominence,
برزت،
large quantities of tea
كميات كبيرة من الشاي
were shipped out from the Port of Quanzhou,
تم شحنها من ميناء تشوانتشو،
bringing the pronunciation of "tea"
تحسين نطق كلمة "شاي"
in Hokkien to the world.
بلغة هوكين للعالم.